<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A suddaine answer to a suddaine moderatour; vvho, directed by reason and no more, expects suddaine peace, or certain ruine. This assures him from Gods mouth, he shall see neither suddaine peace, nor ruine, and yet certaine peace (though never in his way) to them that love truth in sincerity; and certaine ruine to the adversaries thereof. - Pacem te possumus omnes.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94111</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870616</idno>
  <idno type="VID">123009</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240945963</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6141</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E93_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21195</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870616</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99870616e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94111)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123009)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 16:E93[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A suddaine answer to a suddaine moderatour; vvho, directed by reason and no more, expects suddaine peace, or certain ruine. This assures him from Gods mouth, he shall see neither suddaine peace, nor ruine, and yet certaine peace (though never in his way) to them that love truth in sincerity; and certaine ruine to the adversaries thereof. - Pacem te possumus omnes.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.] Printed in the yeare of restauration, when the times alwayes have beene, are, and will be troublous,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642 [i.e. 1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 17.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Povey, Thomas, fl. 1633-1685. --  Moderator expecting sudden peace or certain ruine.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123009:1"/>
            <p>A suddaine ANSWER To a suddaine MODERATOUR; VVho, directed by Reason and no more, expects suddaine PEACE, or Certaine RUINE.</p>
            <p>This assures him from GODS Mouth, he shall see nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>suddaine Peace,</hi> nor <hi>Ruine,</hi> and yet <hi>certaine Peace</hi> (though never in his way) to them that love <hi>Truth</hi> in sincerity; and certaine <hi>Ruine</hi> to the Adversaries thereof.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Pacem Te possumus omnes.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOB. 34, 29.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When He giveth quietnesse, who then can make trouble? and when He hideth His face, who can behold Him? whether it be done against a Nation, or against a man onely.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 16.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When a Mans wayes please the Lord; He maketh his Enemies to be at peace with him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Yeare of <hi>Restauration,</hi> when the times alwayes have beene, are, and will be <hi>Troublous.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:123009:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:123009:2"/>
            <head>REASONS by way of APOLOGY, for this Suddaine ANSWERE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is Suddaine indeed, and, may be, the Reader will say so; the labour of a few houres, stollen away in the Night from sleep: If I nodded over it (which is not my manner, yet) it is pardonable. The Reason it was so Suddaine is besides the quicknesse of the time, the same the Author gives of his MODERATION, <hi>lest it prove like an Almanack, which a few dayes passed puts out of date.</hi> As he had a grave respect to the Times, and to his Reader, so have I too, for I find his Booke (I never yet found his second) as the Ayre is, when some Epidemicall disease is raging, <hi>very catching;</hi> the very Reason this, why this Answer is suddaine. I protest to the Reader, for these Reasons, I could not sleep till I had done it. I must give a Reason also why I give him any Answer at all: Because I find him neither an (empty) <hi>foole,</hi> nor a <hi>railer;</hi> if either of both, I knew my charge, <hi>Answer him not,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 18.36.</p>
            <p>I find him upon confession without <hi>shrift,</hi> a <hi>Moderator,</hi> and in his own Character a <hi>medley.</hi> What is that? I cannot tell my selfe, except such a thing as he makes <hi>Religion, Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace:</hi> neither the one nor the other; nor good, nor bad; but another third thing &amp; that is stark nought; I know not what he is, but like a Meteor he is, he hangs in suspense, and, likely, will fall anon. A well poised lump betwixt ayre and earth, and, because of its predominancie, does fall flat <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>her; and there it would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, breath-out, and die quickly, but that it hath some of the quality we call <hi>heate,</hi> which keeps it from being <hi>key-cold:</hi> Hee might have forborne his <hi>Characters,</hi> for I knew before I came at them, as what himselfe is; so what he makes, <hi>Religion, Truth, Peace, Missellanies</hi> All: <q>and so has uncovered himselfe in the eyes of all the godly, as one of the vain fellowes shamefully uncovered himselfe.</q> The good <hi>Lord</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not this against him, but remember him of that dreadfull threat, <hi>I will shew, &amp;c.</hi>
               <q>To comfort him now a very little, if he were sensible of his danger, I will tell him what his Readers say in his prayes, That he is so brimfull of wit, as that he runs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and full of Reason also:</q> but this is too short of his commendations: I will adde, now I have read and understood him; The Moderator is full of Rhetorick and Oratory too. And let him take all that, but little good that will doe him, till he shall devote all that, in homage and due service to the glory of the <hi>giver.</hi> For my part I like his Rhetorick very well; but three words of <hi>plaine English</hi> I like ten times better: specially at this time.</p>
            <p>Nay, let me tell you I have read 1000. Papers and 1000. too and never met with any I liked better for the Composure (though he Rambles, and so he confesseth) and worse for the <hi>matter,</hi> Strange! you will say. I thought so. I shall have an heavy Censure layed upon me before I begin. Good Reader hold a little, let me speak first, and that I may gaine upon thy Patience; I will assure thee this, That though I have
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:123009:3"/>a naughty, and an untoward heart, and most Deceitfull; yet I shall, in the name of all the true hearted in the world, cleare it to be, in this great businesse, neither <hi>double</hi> nor <hi>cloven,</hi> nor <hi>biased</hi> any way but to the way of <hi>Peace, Truth,</hi> and <hi>Holinesse.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I can force my selfe to beleeve, That the <hi>Moderator</hi> is, as he seemes to be, a man, that loves his Country, and desiers the Peace of it with all his heart; I shall so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with him as a Man, that loves, and desires the same thing, and as heartily as he doth and shall for beare all bitternesse, counting it an unreasonable thing, that a man pursuing Peace should pursue persons, make Warre with them, or make a lie.</p>
            <p>It is true his characters are naught, and, in reading them my spirit was stirred on the suddame not a little: The way also he goes in pursuance of <hi>Peace,</hi> is cleane out of the way of heaven: But yet I beare him witnesse he pursues <hi>Peace</hi> heartily: And the Characters he gives of himselfe and <hi>Truth,</hi> are hearty also, as he feeles his own pulse, and as he conceives of <hi>Truth.</hi> My Answere shall not deale with him there, but it shall keep with him in the maine. As for his Rhetorick and Oratory both, dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon the <hi>good</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> and evill of Warre, I think he might have spared both, for we are flesh and blood also, too sensible of punishment, and senselesse of sinne, we can feele as quick as we heare, or he can speake.</p>
            <p>I would now bespeake his heart towards me, before he reads onward of my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer.</p>
            <p>The Lord give him to look for Truth here on earth, and to find it, which he sayes he looks not to find till he comes to heaven: And such a <hi>Peace</hi> now, which will stand him in stead, when he lies on his death bed: And in pursuance of all this, a better guide, then now he followes, <hi>directed by reason.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>HE that is his own guide has a foole to his Master; and he that is guided by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son has but a blind guide at the best; and yet he will be more blind and fool too, if he will put it out: though holding the <hi>clae</hi> of Reason in his hand, and opening both his eyes, he shall not be able to see wherat to enter, or where to come out of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borinth</hi> of these times.</p>
               <p>But the man speaks not so many words (he thinks) as he does Reason, and yet we could almost wonder, what the man stands reasoning about, and expecting all the while, were it not that he tells us, he is <hi>directed by Reason,</hi> and does <hi>expect suddaint Peace or certaine Ruine.</hi> I protest to him before Almighty <hi>God,</hi> nay from His mouth, he shall see neither: not <hi>a suddaine Peace;</hi> a man directed by Reason cannot expect so: the <hi>motions</hi> are too violant (we take nothing from an All mighty hand, but He is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king inquisition for blood) to be hushed up and still'd on a suddaine. Nor <hi>certaine Ruine,</hi> except to the enemies of <hi>God,</hi> and His <hi>Peace;</hi> and your <hi>mialing</hi> persons, <hi>certaine Ruine</hi> to them also, and it will be <hi>suddaine,</hi> when it comes: but, <hi>directed by reason</hi> we beleeve their <hi>ruine</hi> will not be suddaine neither, not yet: But I make hast to my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, which is a suddain Answere.</p>
               <p>I omit his preamble, It seems the mans eyes are open: and <hi>directed by reason,</hi> what sayes hee?</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:123009:3"/>
               <p> Moder.<hi>The cure is Desperate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Quickly answered, The Disease is so.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>The Chyrurgions doe cut too farre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not sarre enough.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>In letting-out putrifaction, they let out the very Vitalls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It must be so: never any man took a strong purge but precious spirits went out together with the execremen<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. There is some spending of <hi>vitalls,</hi> And yet the Body must be purged, else it dies: I am perswaded his Physitian will tell him so, though <hi>directed but by reason.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>When the</hi> Militia, <hi>the Navy, the Ports were first put into new confiding hands, I looked upon that action like to that cloud, which seemed as a mans hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Who bid</hi> him <hi>doe so?</hi> His eyes misguide him, and his Reason too; was then the first appearance of a cloud, and but such an appearance, as a mans hand then? The Lord knows, and his People also. That the cloud was up, as high as the Sun at noon and a thick cloud also, and it darkened the heaven long before. And there was no other way directed by Reason that could be taken to prevent a shower of blood from falling (like the raine we call <hi>Spouts</hi>) [when the raine falls not broken into drops, we call it the [<hi>pouts.</hi> Sr. <hi>W. R. Hist. l.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.] upon the Church, truly so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led but by putting the <hi>Militia</hi> into <hi>new</hi> (for the old were naught and rotten) <hi>confiding hands,</hi> for the others could not be trusted, they have declared themselves the betrayers of <hi>God,</hi> His <hi>Christ</hi> and their Country.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>The more active of the Parliament are accused of Treason.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> We grant that.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>The Kings adversaries are impeached by the Parliament for Traitors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That is true too, Traitors sure enough, that will advise their King to betray his great Trust, <hi>Lawes, Liberties, Religion,</hi> and all into his enemies hands.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Thus the Scene begins to alter, and instead of Reforming, the Parliament is busied, almost puzled in saving (for so they call it) a distressed Church and State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We call it so indeed, and the Parliament are <hi>busied,</hi> nay, as the man <hi>directed by reason</hi> sayes, <hi>puzled</hi> too in <hi>saving</hi> of it. <hi>I pray heaven</hi> (it is the Players phrase, good, but abused too often) blesse them in this <hi>puzling worke,</hi> the proper worke of a Parliament indeed, but of God to finish it: and because it is such a puzling worke, The <hi>God</hi> of wisdome lead them into all wisdome to the execution of their charge, the <hi>cutting off</hi> that Viperous generation of men, those <hi>troublers,</hi> who are eating out the bowels of their Mother: and let those, that have ingaged themselves upon this <hi>puzling worke,</hi> the saving <hi>a distressed Church and State</hi> know, they shall not lose their <hi>labour of love,</hi> and <hi>worke of Faith,</hi> though <hi>Israel</hi> be not <hi>saved,</hi> which were but a little short of Blasphemy to doubt.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Common Law called</hi> Salus Populi, <hi>and Statute Law, enacted by nature, called</hi> Lex Necessitatis, <hi>must warrant all their undertaking, and justifie all manner of severity and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No but it shall not, but the contrary, It shall condemne all undertakings to distresse the Church and State; and eurse from heaven all manner of violence upon the people: And it shall warrant and justifie all undertaking against those <hi>miscreants,</hi> who have so wasted their owne Country, and eate out the heart of their own Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:123009:4"/>
               <p> M. <hi>The most eminent discovery of this warre was about the Town of</hi> Hull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Be it so; but a Discovery there was sixe yeares agoe, when the <hi>Service-Booke</hi> was sent into <hi>Scotland;</hi> and quickly after the Sword: Then (to look no farther back) there was a Discovery plaine enough, and more then an appearance of a cloud and thick darknesse; it gathered towards the North, and what if we grant it was most <hi>eminently</hi> seen before the Town of <hi>Hull?</hi> we grant it; and this withall must be granted too for it is eminently discovered also, <hi>That the ground of the quarrell is not whether the Town of</hi> Hull <hi>shall be the Kings: but whether this Kingdome shall be the</hi> Lords <hi>(i.e.) whether the</hi> Lord Christ <hi>shall have this Kingdome for his Possession. I will venture my soule upon it, and it is more to me then all the Kingdomes of the world.</hi> This is the ground of the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, and <hi>eminently</hi> known so to be. I look for a Viall of wrath now, and the Spouts of His Displeasure to be powred down; yet I am secure about it, for the Kingdome is <hi>the Lords:</hi> Let the <hi>Lord Christ</hi> alone to Rule there, He will Reigne most gloriously amidst His enemies: He is a <hi>strong Redeemer,</hi> and they that will not submit to His Golden Scepter, shall be broken to pieces with His rod of Iron.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>The King has caught the affections of his Subjects with Promises and Protestations, to defend the property and liberty of his Subjects, though Promises are but shadowes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are so indeed, and no trusting in such shadows, but whether he hath caught the affections of his Subjects under these shadows I think it is scarse questioned.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>But if he has caught his Subjects under these shadowes, how much more then will his Subjects be his when these promised Elessings shall be theirs in earnest?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There needs no Question: they will be all his, when he makes all good which he sayes; when he speaks that they may see him; good words realized by good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then they will be all his hand and tongue, and heart and all, the truest Subjects to their King that are in the world, as long as he is the <hi>Lords,</hi> keeps to Him, his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster in heaven,</hi> and will intrust himselfe, and his people under His shadow, which is the <hi>shadow of the Almighty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M <hi>What advantage have we had by any thing that has been acted by the Sword?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We cannot boast of Advantages though we have I thinke as much advantage therby as we looked for from such an instrument, an opressing thing where ever it is: and yet I will say we have had and have a very great advantage by it. It hath kept the Sword of the adversaries from some of our throats; and the Cause of <hi>Christ</hi> from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing trampled upon by the foot of Pride, like myre in the street: And though we are a wasted peeled people indeed, yet, <hi>blessed be our God, not</hi> like <hi>Ireland;</hi> we are not yet deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up as a <hi>prey</hi> to the adversaries teeth; he cannot execute the fiercenes of his wrath upon us: and this Advantage we have by the Sword. In short, we have the very same advantage by the Sword now, which <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and the builders had in those <hi>troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> times; if they had not had the Sword in the one hand, they could not have buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the other: I know I have but a hard pull of it, to draw advantage from the Sword: but yet this Advantage we have, as afore said: Therfore the <hi>Moderator</hi> does us a plausible wrong here, in telling us in his foolish pity, <hi>that we are abused.</hi> No, we are not abused in his sence nor after his thoughts, though <hi>abused</hi> we are, and most notoriously abused: by whom? By those from whom we can expect no right, such Sonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> they are: so much to our <hi>abuse,</hi> and the <hi>Moderators</hi> pity. At this standing we may gather some Flowers of Rhetorick, and observe some straines of Oratory bestowed upon that old Theame, <hi>The Tyranny of Warre:</hi> and in passage he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123009:4"/>bestowes pretty civill language upon the Parliament somtimes, but that is his craft, that he may give them some by-blowes, presently after undiscerned, and truly his smiting is very smart, and as palpable as a man <hi>biassed,</hi> we know which way. Let him goe his way, he sayes;</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Though the times are so catching, we can scarce call any thing our own, yet, I hope, they will let us enjoy the use of our reason still which shall alwayes lead my faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, good reason; enjoy it, and use it, I pray you, and your faith too, but no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son it should lead your faith, but rather follow: but take your course, and goe on.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>And expectation in such open affaires, as these: my Reason and faith both having set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled me, and made me obstinate in this opinion, that a peace warily concluded on by an accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation must be the happyest issue that can be given to these differences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Look ye, the <hi>Moderatour</hi> is an obstinate Man, he cannot moderate well: but I will doe him the favour to passe that by; we have all now, and can eye his full scope. I shall goe forward a little, and returne in good time: and he shall goe on how with little interruption, for they be matters of great Difference, but not controverted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us: he tells us how he came to be settled in his opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> from the Aimes in this Warre (wherein we must observe his <hi>modesty</hi>) The grounds or causes of it, (where we must discerne his <hi>charity,</hi>) That he will think Religion, Laws, Liberties, the moving cause therof, for that's confessed, though <hi>not agreed upon.</hi> Then he falls into his Rhetorick againe, as if <hi>words</hi> could make us more sensible, what Warre is, then blowes. I assure you, he is deceived, we need not his Rhetorick, nor Oratory neither, our <hi>sense</hi> is quick enough at that point, <hi>God knowes.</hi> Then he assureth when <hi>all is done, there will be no victory:</hi> yes, but there will, for when all is done, <hi>Truth</hi> will prevaile, and be more glorious the more it was darkened, dashed upon and opposed. I passe-by his by-blowes, rather his rude dashing upon the Parliament: then up againe, wipes his mouth and away. But I cannot for beare the mentioning of this, touching his Religion (for it is not ours I hope.) <hi>It is many times but a servant to other designes, and so it shall be followed,</hi> and this is his allowance. Truly, if I would speake here in so cleare a case, I would speak cleane contrary that all Designes should be servants to <hi>Religion,</hi> should serve to usher-in that: would we have our Laws better exercised, our liberties more enlarged, and secured? yes indeed would we, What, by the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering Sword? O no, the thought of it makes our hearts to bleed: but yet this is the designe to bring in Religion, to settle, ensure, and secure that, as in <hi>Nehemiah</hi>'s dayes.</p>
               <p>He goes on, I cannot observe his method, for I see none: he deales truly with us in this, for he tells us he <hi>rambled,</hi> he does indeed, let him ramble-on; if he goes so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I must <hi>ramble</hi>-after: but he falls in his way upon the <hi>Remonstrance of the Kingdome,</hi> and censures it at his pleasure. He would not have had the vile Counsellors disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; nor the Malignant generation, when it was boldly affirmed there were none such in the land; nor any in <hi>Ireland</hi> say we as truly.</p>
               <p>Then he gives a shrewd blow at the Parliament, againe telling us, what keeps it from <hi>staggering;</hi> but there he is quite out, for that, which he mentions, will make them fall, when right Aimes, the glory of their God, and the good of this people, shall make them stand firme and steddy, upheld by an Allmighty Arme. Then he falls upon Arguments of <hi>advantage</hi> and <hi>disadvantage.</hi> The Advantage the King hath (for that syllable has as much advantage as another Army;) The advantage the Scots
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:123009:5"/>had in their yeare; and the disadvantage-ground we stand upon; and here he speaks not reasonably as a man directed by Reason; yet truly the Advantages on the one side are so considerable; the disadvantage on the other side so great, that surely the man, who is <hi>directed by reason,</hi> and has no other guide, will be stark mad with Reason. But let me put in a word to make him sober, there be great advantages on their side, great disadvantages on this side; Treasure spent, and spirits spent, and all spent: see now and spy out, on whose side Truth is. It is but a syllable neither but more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable then many Armies: on whose side is truth? on the stronger side (you will say as a Moderator) that hath all advantages in sight. Nay, I doe not beleeve it, but leave it not to my conceit, for I shall not declare my mind now at that point, but spy it out on whose side Truth is, there is the advantage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the King can worke like a King, and bestow Honours like a King,</hi> &amp;c. He can so, and he is more bound to God that hath so enabled him but God (one syllable also and no more, yet of more Advantage than all the Armes in the Heaven, Earth, or Sea) can doe more, hee can worke like a <hi>God;</hi> give like a <hi>God;</hi> sustaine like a <hi>God,</hi> all like a <hi>God,</hi> where <hi>God</hi> is there is the advantage, spie it out, it is discernable, where <hi>Truth</hi> is there is <hi>God,</hi> and where He is there is there is the advantage; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he will goe on merrily for all the trouble, that is directed <hi>by Faith:</hi> he not so, that <hi>is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by Reason:</hi> vet we will go on.</p>
               <p>The next step he falls upon <hi>Charactars,</hi> gives us a cleare-one of himselfe, of <hi>Truth</hi> also, and so he hath dishonoured himselfe, and thrust back Peace: <hi>God</hi> give him to see it, and pardon the iniquitie of His Servant: Above all, The <hi>Lord</hi> unvaile his eyes at this high point that he may seek for <hi>truth</hi> here find it, and stand up for it, resist the opposers of it even unto Death (if the case so require) for so he must doe on earth, else he shall never find heaven as he expects, and <hi>truth</hi> there.</p>
               <p>Now we are at the end, we will returne, and according to his desire, <hi>owne Reason on which side soever we shall finde it.</hi> and seeing it leads us to an <hi>accommodation,</hi> thereby to finde peac, thither we will returne, for there is all the matter, and kirnell of the businesse.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That a Peace warily coucluded on by accommodation must be the happiest issue that can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to these Differences.</hi> Here the <hi>Moderatour</hi> hath a great advantage of mee, though what I speake, shall be directed by Reason and by something like it, but much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; yet I say, he hath a great advantage, for speaking for a <hi>State-Peace</hi> as he doth for a State-Religion, and Truth (all which I abominate as much as he allowes) hee is more to the <hi>Genius</hi> of the State and more in shew for the Peace of his Country than I can b<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; and yet I will not stoope an inch to him at those high points, my love to Religion, to Peace, to Truth to my King to his Kingdome: why then must wee heare so ill in undertakings of this kind that we are sonnes of <hi>Mars,</hi> wee call for a sword, we delight in bloud speake to us of Peace we are for Warre, are content to see our Country rent asunder with her owne hands? A heavie censure this; were there any of that wee call <hi>Truth</hi> in it as the searcher of all hearts knowes, there is none, we appeale to him in it (I speake in the name of all the true hearted in the World) He knowes we seeke Peace and pursue it, as heartily as King <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> did, when a proud adversarie was before his wall: so heartily, and yet the doubt may be, whether not too eagerly, and therefore it flies from us: but I say, we pursue it, our consciences b<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are us witnesse, our <hi>God</hi> also, wee wssh for peace as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123009:5"/>earnestly, as the husband-man does, whose Horse is taken from him, hee cannot plough his heart too, he is carelesse to sow, because he knowes not who shall reape: so the <hi>Moderatour,</hi> we tell him; we desire Peace as the husband-man does; if he will beleeve it, and why should he not? If the husband-man plouges not, hee cannot sow, if he sow not he cannot reape; then we must want bread &amp; feele the want soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then hee: I am willing to insist a little upon this first, to cleare us of this dirt cast into our faces, that we doe not wish our Countries peace; I tell him againe, for I would speake very feelingly, we will bid as much to purchase Peace, as the Countries will doe, which have been hurried and spoiled; we will give as much as they for <hi>Peace,</hi> if we may except one thing, but it is more considerable then an Army, what is that? A thing not much enquired after, but we call it <hi>Truth;</hi> wee thanke <hi>God</hi> he hath given us so much discerning of it, that wee can put an esteeme upon it, that we can count of it though but a monosyllable, more considerable then Armies, which the Country-men for the most part, cannot doe, so much to blame are their Teachers, we speake this with hearts griefe, and in the dearest affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to our Country mens soules, and say, except but that we call <hi>Truth,</hi> and we call <hi>God</hi> to record upon our soules, we will give as much as all the Countries give: nay, &amp; yet I will speak no proud word we will give as much for Peace as this mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man will do, so he will not give <hi>Truth</hi> for it, which we may suspect by his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, he will rather part with then his money. At this one <hi>syllable</hi> only, but so consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, we shall differ with him if different in mind from us, and turne our backes upon him &amp; yet shall shew our selvs as sensible of the blessings of <hi>Peace,</hi> and the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of warre as the <hi>Moderatour</hi> can be, and need not his flowers of Rhetorick to expresse our <hi>sense</hi> that way our feeling, I meane which is the quickest <hi>sense</hi> we have, and I have expressed it already as <hi>feelingly</hi> as I can when we approve our selves at that point, as tender as is the husband-man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why then hearken</hi> sayes he <hi>to reason, to an Accommodation.</hi> What is that? <hi>To A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate this difference by some middle way, wherin either party shall remit somewhat of the rigour of those termes in which they now stand.</hi> This is an <hi>Acommodation</hi> and the <hi>way</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and the <hi>Moderatour</hi> is so <hi>obstinately</hi> resolved upon it, that he thinks he hath spoken all, and is in the right way to <hi>Peace,</hi> and that there is no other way, when as the very Truth is which will appeare presently, <hi>Toto Caelo errat,</hi> The man is quite out of the way, and if I might expresse it so, as one doth he is <hi>heavenly wide,</hi> for first, hee takes it for granted, that there are but two parties offended, the King, and his friends; the <hi>Parliament</hi> and their friends: That is a great mistake, for all the <hi>Powers</hi> in Heaven and Hell are parties here, and offended greatly: <hi>Michaell,</hi> and his Angells, <hi>Belze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bub,</hi> and his Angells, nor these onely, there is a <hi>principall Verbe,</hi> (whom hee hath l<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ft out) one syllable indeed but infinitely concerned and engaged in this businesse and of more advantage then are all the World: And there is a <hi>second Person,</hi> equally concerned too whom for honours sake I will name, <hi>Ephesians</hi> 1.12. far above all <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality, and power, and might, and Dominion, and every name, that is named, not onely in this world,</hi> but also in <hi>that which is to come:</hi> all these he hath left out of the Treaty, the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>the Sonne.</hi> These two the <hi>Moderatour</hi> hath (whether willingly, or ignorantly I judge not, ignorantly I thinke) left out of the Treaty, acknowledging but two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties offended; And so though he bee all for <hi>a middle way,</hi> yet hee hath mistaken his way utterly. And now he is more than halfe perswaded, that no man will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123009:6"/>to answer him: why? Because the Answer he thinkes, will run point blanck a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Peace,</hi> that Mother-Blessing, so comprehensive, that it containes all things which make a Nation honourable, and the head of Kingdomes: And hee will clash against sacred Majesty too, for he will not abate an inch from the height of that <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious</hi> Reformation, which the Parliament Intend, and carry all levell unto.</p>
               <p>I shall by <hi>Gods</hi> good hand upon me walke straight on &amp; unbyassed in a <hi>middle way,</hi> indeed, not gazing upon or prying into, what the King and Parliament do; <hi>The Lord blesse King and Parl</hi> say I and make them of one mind &amp; one heart, &amp; so direct them in all their wayes that in all they do they may have the answer of a good conscience from wichin, how ever things stand or fall without. But I say I will not meddle with these State-affaires, my foote shall not enter into this <hi>maze:</hi> Something the <hi>Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour</hi> will force from me anon, which will reflect upon sacred Majesty, but it shall be spoken with the clearest evidence of Truth and love to his Peace and Crowne that is conceiveable.</p>
               <p>Therefore to undeceive the <hi>Moderatours</hi> over-hasty expectation, I will tell him now the way I will goe &amp; then goe on in it; I will apply my self to that third party <hi>God</hi> for three persons are but one <hi>God</hi> whom the <hi>Moderatour</hi> hath left out of the treaty for <hi>Peace;</hi> and shall make it cleare in a few words to all that will see; that hee is a <hi>Syllable</hi> of such concernment in this busines, that till he be put into the Treatie, till he be treated with and in his own way there will be no way made for <hi>Peace</hi> &amp; I must tell him this also by the way, that this <hi>third party</hi> is, in a treatie of this Nature a hard Master, and will hold us with some rigour to his Termes, and <hi>Imperious</hi> demands and cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure a <hi>middle way;</hi> which, notwitstanding, a World of men doe now beat upon, and with all their might bend unto but if it be the right way then <hi>God</hi> hath decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved mee; and if it be <hi>Gods Peace</hi> they seek after; then this is not facred Scripture which I shall now propose to your eye; <hi>It is a day of trouble and of treading downe, and of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, by the Lord God of Hosts; and thou didst looke in that day to the Armour of the house of the forrest.</hi> I observe hence, that <hi>Iudah</hi> was greatly distressed at this time: Peace seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be quite taken from them; and faine they would recover it again but they were quite out of the way; a great blame lies upon them, what was it for? not because they looked to the Armour of the house of the forrest, which house of <hi>Armory S<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> built for his whole Kingdome 1 <hi>King.</hi> 7.2. nor are they blamed for spying out <hi>the breaches of the City of</hi> David <hi>which were many,</hi> and looking to all meanes to stop the same, and to fortifie themselves they were not blamed for this, for all this was wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done and the better, had it been don sooner. But for this they are blamed; <hi>Thou didst looke to the Armour &amp;c. but yee have not looked unto the maker thereof, neither had respect unto him, &amp;c. v.</hi> 11. They looked not unto God in all this; they had no respect unto him, and yet they would have Peace, and would be safe, well fortified against their Enemy; not considering that <hi>God</hi> was their Adversary; <hi>He powred upon them through that Viall the fury of his Anger and the strength of battell.</hi> Esay 42.25. and he must be <hi>looked unto,</hi> a respect must be had unto him, before ever they shall have peace on the Earth: and it must bee obtained by <hi>weeping and mourning, Esay</hi> 22.12, whereunto the <hi>Lord</hi> called them by those evills He inflicted upon them. But we read there how unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the people were, and it is just our case now; we comply with the <hi>Moderatour,</hi> here we are of his judgement for we looke to every thing and b<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd our selves every way, but we <hi>looke not unto the Lord God,</hi> we have not a respect unto him.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:123009:6"/>
               <p> And this I thought fit to premise in more words, that I may be the shorter after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; but especially, that the people may know, wee wish their Peace: as hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily as themselves can do, onely they must know also unto whom they must <hi>looke,</hi> and have a <hi>respect</hi> unto, if they looke to have their expectation answered; for the <hi>Lord</hi> gives <hi>Peace,</hi> it comes from His <hi>hand;</hi> as the inward Peace which cannot bee <hi>plundered;</hi> so the outward also: the <hi>Lord, God</hi> of Peace give his People both through the <hi>Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ</hi> our Peace-maker, and is called the <hi>Repairer of the breach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And so I returne into our way againe in the pursuit of Peace, by way of <hi>Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation,</hi> and here;</p>
               <p>We protest againe in the presence of GOD, That our eares are open unto it, and our eyes spying out a way whereat to enter in and come fairely out with an Olive branch in our hands, for it seemes a Labyrinth: And yet wee could have an easie passage, if the Peace sought for were a mans Peace, in his hands to give; or the sword, we would have sheathed, mans sword; we could then make up the difference by an <hi>Accommodation.</hi> But the Peace is GODS <hi>Peace,</hi> whom the Moderator, the Inquisitor also (likely one and the same) hath left out of the Treaty, GODS <hi>Peace</hi> I say in his hands to give when he pleaseth, and we must wait his time the <hi>Sword</hi> is in mans hand indeed, as the <hi>Axe</hi> is and the <hi>Rod</hi> is; but it is Gods Sword wherewith he is avenging the quarrell of his Covenant, Mans the Viall, God powres it out; we beg, and intreat and pray, saying, <hi>Rest and be still; Ier.</hi> 47.6. The Answer is still, <hi>It cannot rest:</hi> The Lord knowes the Father of our Spirits, the God of all flesh; He knowes we would have Peace; but we know no way in the world how to accommodate it, but by making Peace with God (who is offended) removing what is grievous to his Eyes and by breaking downe that which breaks <hi>His heart; zach.</hi> 6.9. And we are confident, till this be done, <hi>valiant ones shall cry out,</hi> and <hi>Embassadors</hi> of Peace shall weep bitterly <hi>Is.</hi> 33 7. as once they did; for ask from one end of the heaven to the other; but it will suffice toaske from the beginning of Gods book to the end of the same. The Answer will be <hi>No Peace</hi> till <hi>God</hi> be at peace; till we have made His <hi>Christ</hi> our <hi>Friend:</hi> And this cannot be, till we have done as aforesaid, removed that which makes Him our <hi>Enemy;</hi> and our <hi>weapons turne back wherewith we fight even against Babilon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I protest before the living <hi>God</hi> (indeed I am earnest, and is there not a cause? I am pleading for <hi>God,</hi> He needs me not, not such a poore worme, but it would make a dumb man speake, heareing that he who stands for all, stands now as a <hi>Cipher,</hi> nay lesse then that, He gaines not a place, he is not so much as once named in this <hi>Treaty,</hi> nor is the removing of those things so much as mentioned, which make Him our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versarie; I am pleading for <hi>God,</hi> for his Cause, his Truth, his Peace, his King, his Kingdome; in a dearer affection my deceitfull heart tells me to my Country, then is expressable.) I protest then before the <hi>living God,</hi> that if so be wee should stand and aske every day from the moneth of <hi>March</hi> to the next the next year; <hi>Is it peace?</hi> the Answer will be as often repeated, <hi>No,</hi> no peace, no <hi>Accommodation.</hi> nor never will be, till you are come up to <hi>God,</hi> to his Termes, to <hi>make Peace with him,</hi> through that <hi>middle was, God, Man, Iesus Christ:</hi> I pray you hearken to it and consider on it.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>There is a State Religion, which may be a</hi> Servant to other designes, <hi>and such a Truth too, and such a</hi> Peace <hi>also.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> The Moderatour saves so and gives us Characters of all these (as of himself too) but some thing like <hi>Reason</hi> will not give me leave to thinke, that such a Religion is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:123009:7"/>any better then no Religion: or that such a <hi>Peace</hi> is not more destructive than war. our Peace with that, where with we should have warre; and warring against <hi>God</hi> of whom we should seek <hi>Peace,</hi> hath caused all our troubles, it cannot lessen them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the Peace is not the worse comming through the Princes hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, but much the better, so he seek it too as we must at <hi>Gods hand,</hi> and by that <hi>middle way</hi> which <hi>God</hi> found out, thereby to declare the unsearchable riches of his <hi>Wisedome, Mercy, Grace.</hi> It is supposed now that in seeking Peace at the right doore, the <hi>extra</hi> or <hi>intra pro<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ens,</hi> that which will hinder the obtaining our suite must be removed, even what ever provocations there are before Gods eyes.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>And he is a gracious Prince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I will pray, <hi>God save the King,</hi> and blesse him, with the blessings of His right, and His left hand, and having given some grace, <hi>dd more,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>Remember we not the Declarations he hath made? no Prince ever gave such engagements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes we Remember very well And that others have said almost as much, and have done almost as little, But let the <hi>Moderatour</hi> goe on: though he hath lost his guide and is quite out of the way.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>He is an envious man that would not make a bonesire for every Declaration he hath sent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I dare not say so, that he is an envious man, that will not make a <hi>bonefire:</hi> I think he may be a good man and yet think a bonefire an unworthy expression of true Joy. I would forbear farther Answer here, but I cannot &amp; faine I would speak <hi>abstractly,</hi> and in the generall (though there is deceit) but I must speak as the case requires, in truth of heart A Rulers Declaration of his Grace, Trust, and Service is to no purpose except to make a Bonefire, if it be not followed, with Truth and Action: The higher the person is the more he stands charged from the mouth of <hi>God,</hi> and his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample so to practice, that he may be seene to speake, <hi>He hath spoken with his mouth, and fulfilled with his hand, is</hi> foure times repeated [1 <hi>King.</hi> 8 15. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 6] To the prayse of <hi>God</hi> Himselfe, <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, Higgaion Selah,</hi> also words seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously to be considered on, I will adde this; good words are good <hi>Remonstrances of</hi> of a good mind; when Actions are not <hi>Contra-Remonstrances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>We could not see our season, we might have closed with the King, when hee seemed to open his Armes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Truly if I could forbear now (but my words are as fire within me) I would an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer nothing; because I have two affections, which are almost become passions, so stirring they are within mee at this very time, <hi>Anger</hi> and <hi>feare;</hi> I am angry with the <hi>Moderatour,</hi> and for very just Reason, I could be shrew his fingers for opening the Kings Armes so wide; and I could wish he had bit his tongue, when he told us, they <hi>seemed to open</hi> and no more; so some <hi>Persons</hi> have done, and an <hi>Engine</hi> also, they seemed to open their Armes to embrace, and killed in embraceing [<hi>Philetae amplexu strangalant: Sen:</hi> Hist: of the world, <hi>Page</hi> 532. I have overcome my <hi>Anger,</hi> I will by <hi>Gods</hi> help overcome my feare too, why should I be afraid to speake, speaking from <hi>Gods</hi> mouth, and in a zeale for my King and Country, guided by knowledge? I am constrained; the <hi>Lord</hi> knowes I am, for I will appeale to Him, beholding with open face, the Sword lifted up like <hi>Abrahams</hi> hand, over <hi>Isaack,</hi> to kill him and his Mother too (that is the purpose) a dumb man spake then &amp; why not I now? I will open my mouth and speake; <hi>It shall not be told to Posterity</hi> (It is the <hi>Moderatours</hi> Reason) why he spake, and I love my King &amp; Country as well as he, <hi>Peace</hi> too &amp; Truth also)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123009:7"/>
                  <hi>That we doe all wilfully blind the eyes of our Reason, and will not see that which is palpable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us; I must speake that our Children may not tell their children that their Parents were a poore naked People, blind too, and dumb also;</hi> In answer then to these <hi>open Armes;</hi> This I say first That next to the open Armes of <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Eather</hi> of our <hi>Lord Iesus Christ,</hi> and in him so wide opened towards us; next to those <hi>Almighty Armes</hi> would his poore People, slie for refuge into the Armes of his Majestie; and they will <hi>force</hi> themselves to believe they are open to defend them his distressed People: but if they should come, they cannot force themselves to believe, that those at his elbow, will not close his Armes upon them, even when he is opening to receive them and so strangle them out-right, which is quickly done, for they are more than halfe dead already; because his Armes and heart are so shut against his good people. What have they done? Hee that searcheth the heart and trieth the Reines knoweth, they know not themselves guilty of any thing against his sacred Majestie, wherefore his Armes should bee closed against them: and opened towards his, and their Enemies. They have loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked narrowly into their hearts, what they have done or spoken, which might close his Majesties armes against them, and they finde nothing that they have done, or spoken, but <hi>good</hi> for him before the <hi>Lord,</hi> and therein they have not beene silent night nor day, and that is their comfort.</p>
               <p>M <hi>His Majesties Armes seeme open to receive them, why doe they not come?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> His good People, those that are his indeed, cannot trust <hi>shewes,</hi> and <hi>seemings;</hi> When his armes are wide open to those about him, his and their Enemies, his Armes cannot so much as <hi>seeme</hi> to open towards his poore people I will give him, who is not willingly Ignorant good Reason for this, when I have told him what befell my selfe once, which will instruct the ignorant more then <hi>Reason</hi> can small things will illustrate great. I came once to my friends house, whose heart I knew could close with me as mine with him; and entring his Out-Court, out flies a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stive Dog to my face, by a <hi>Providence</hi> I withstood his first onset, and presently help came in; for I was at my friends house, whose Armes were open to receive me, hee saw well what a greeting I had, therefore he greeted me the more heartily and I him: but I told him Sir, the Proverb holds not, <hi>love me love my Dog,</hi> you must <hi>trusse-up</hi> your Dog, else you know who will never come at you, though you could open your Armes as wide as the two <hi>Poles</hi> are distant; <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South:</hi> he beleeved me, else he had not shewed himselfe a wise man, or a friend.</p>
               <p>He that will open his Armes to receive his friend, will take care, to remove all Jealousies his friend may so much as conceit to the contrary; much more will hee take care; that his Dogs mouth may be muzzled-up, if not trussed up by the neck.</p>
               <p>To speake out, for so I am resolved from the mouth of <hi>God;</hi> his sacred Majesty cannot open his Armes to receive his Subjects into favour and grace: he cannot so much as <hi>seeme</hi> so to doe, so I say directed by Reasons. more strongly bottomed then are the <hi>everlasting hills,</hi> and perpetuall Mountaines.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He cannot open his Armes to his poore Subjects, till he hath opened his heart to <hi>God</hi> in confession, that <hi>God</hi> made him King in <hi>his stead,</hi> set him upon <hi>His Throne,</hi> [<hi>Gods Throne;</hi>] put the Testimony into his hand, his <hi>Law-Booke</hi> before his eyes, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him to doe thereafter, to be a <hi>Father</hi> to his Country, <hi>Lord Protector</hi> there, to doe his People all right, to suffer no wrong to be done unto them, for therefore <hi>God</hi> made him King, and set him upon <hi>His Throne;</hi> till the King hath opened his heart to <hi>God</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:123009:8"/>in confession of his owne sinnes, the sinnes of his people also; their Idolatrous wayes and Courses, which brings a sword to lay his Land waste: till he hath so don, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not truly open his Armes to his poore People.</p>
               <p>Whether the King hath done this or no he is to be accountable to <hi>God</hi> alone. Be it so, though that is nothing to our purpose; but till he hath made this confession in sinceritie and Truth, he cannot so much as <hi>seeme</hi> to open his Armes towards his Subjects indeed and in Truth: And when he shall make this his confession betwixt <hi>God,</hi> and his owne soule, then will the consequence there from be as discernable to his poore Subjects, and as operative towards them for good, as <hi>light</hi> is, and <hi>life</hi> is, both which will manifest themselves where ever they are: till this be done he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not open his Armes towards his poore Subjects.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor till hee shut his eares, and his heart to <hi>vile Councellours,</hi> I say vile Councellours, who make the King rush upon the drawne sword, and practice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Law of Heaven, and the Law of the Land, and are themselves as the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening Wolves;</hi> he cannot open his Armes to his distressed people, nor his eare to their crye, till he hath closed his care, and his heart fast up against those vile men, nay not till he hath <hi>cut</hi> them short by the shoulders, or trussed them up by the neck.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nor till he has barred up his heart against the <hi>Councells</hi> of her, that hath laine in his bosome, for she drives the trade of the World, and is a Chiefe, and principall A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent therein: To dethrone the <hi>Lord Iesus Christ,</hi> and to advance <hi>Antichrist,</hi> (it will never be, but it is the great designe, Trade and project the World is now driving on: And she an active instrument, for carrying on that Designe with all her might.) The King cannot open his Armes truly, and heartily to receive in his poore distres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed people, till he hath barred up his heart against the Councell of her that hath layn in his bosome, nor which was first, and it shall be last.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Till he walkes contrary to himselfe, as contrary as were the streames in the <hi>South,</hi> when they were turned backe: as contrary as <hi>Manasseh</hi> was to himselfe, after he was brought into the Thornes, and was humbled: till his heart bee turned backe, till he walke contrary to himselfe; till he shall confesse his imquity, and the iniquity of his people with their trespasse, which they trespassed against the <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> also they have walked contrary unto the Lord and that the <hi>Lord</hi> hath also walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed contrary unto him, till he shall confesse this, and thus open his heart before the <hi>Lord,</hi> he cannot open his Armes toward his good people. And according to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure of these words, his good people have done for themselves, and doe, and do speak for their King also thereafter night and day before the <hi>Lord;</hi> and what they speak before the <hi>Lord</hi> I will not shame to speake before men. I will adde, whosoever he is, that is to make answer to such a passage as this, and does not speak according to the Tenure and purpose of these words, the truth is not in him, he holds it <hi>in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes Rom.</hi> 1.18. and he is an Enemy to his King and Kingdom; to the Soule of his Soule, and the life of our lives; the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Faith of the Gospell.</hi> I have spoken according to my charge the <hi>Oracle</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> But yet if in the judgement of any, as one of the fooles in <hi>Israel,</hi> It is for <hi>Israels</hi> sake, that they may have <hi>Peace,</hi> if as as a man besides himselfe, it is for <hi>Israels</hi> sake too, in abundance of affection to <hi>Israel</hi> that <hi>Israel</hi> may have Peace, Peace with <hi>God</hi> and then peace from <hi>God,</hi> even from His Hand, which cannot be till our <hi>uncir cumcised hearts</hi> are humbled for our <hi>whorish waves,</hi> therein warring against the <hi>God</hi> of our Peace: No Peace I say againe to Prince or people, till there be a <hi>giraing with sackcloth and a wallowing in dust</hi> [<hi>Jer.</hi> 6.26.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123009:8"/>for our shedding of blood, &amp; provoking the <hi>Lord</hi> with <hi>Images &amp; strange vanities.</hi> And this I have desired to speak to my own &amp; every mans heart in as expresse terms as <hi>Isaac</hi> the munk spake to <hi>Valence</hi> the <hi>Emperor</hi> who told him that things wen: very crosse No marvail said <hi>Isaac,</hi> for you walk crosse to <hi>God,</hi> You shall have no Peace while you warre with Him. You have hurried the faithfull Pastors from their flockes, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store them againe and cease thou to rebell against <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> will cease to fight against thee [<hi>Tripart. Hist. lib:</hi> 9. <hi>Cap.</hi> 13] Thus plainely I have spoken that we may have Peace, Peace now, when warre is at the gate, peace then when pangs are upon us a peace that cannot be plundered. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I look for peace, when I looke to see fire like another <hi>deluge</hi> round about me, when others shall be at their wits end for expectation: I resolved therefore to speake out, and plainely for the Peace of my King, and Coontry, that he and his people might be shewne the <hi>excellent way</hi> to accommodate the same. Againe, I live if I doe live, by Truth in my heart; I would dye when I must dye with Truth in my mouth; then I looke to goe to Heaven, and finde <hi>Truth</hi> there, and live with Truth for ever. These thoughts made me <hi>obstinately</hi> setled, that I would speak out the Truth, and for <hi>Truth</hi> so <hi>helpe me God Amen.</hi> I have two words more; I have bent my answer to the maine scope the Moderator has in his eyes the <hi>Peace</hi> of the King and Kingdome, we both make way after the same thing, and goe both crosse; He would have <hi>Peace</hi> [by an Accommodation while we stand in defiance with Heaven: I would have <hi>peace</hi> made with <hi>God</hi> first; the whole matter is committed to Him, Who is the <hi>Way</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> and the <hi>Life;</hi> for He is judge himselfe. Other things may seeme to require answer but truely I tooke care onely to finde out his scope, and thereunto to bend my answer; he glanceth at this &amp; at that; &amp; clasheth here and there, and takes a libertie of conceit, yet will make us beleeve He conceits the best; and will not censure, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede that is a point of wisdome. And yet we have warrant to beleeve that the Aymes of the <hi>Lords</hi> servants have beene strait and levell to His glory and His peoples good else His Hand had not beene so with them hitherto. If I have any discerning or can make any discovery upon the wayes of men, and finde them off and on I pray <hi>God,</hi> as well as I can, to settle them: If I finde them constant to themselves to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>his Cause,</hi> I say and I am sure of what I say, <hi>after they have sufferod a while, the Lord will make them and their worke perfect</hi> [1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10.] For there shall be no worke done for the <hi>Lord</hi> which he will not finish and recompence those that have laboured in it. There are disadvantages now but <hi>one God</hi> is sufficient to make all up, a scattering now; there will be a time of <hi>gathering,</hi> A Crosse wayes and wills now; <hi>God</hi> is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a <hi>Method</hi> of them. That he is not plucking downe his house, he assures you in the word of a <hi>God,</hi> who tenders his house and honshold, better then any father on earth can do. And now that my thoughts are upon <hi>Gods</hi> House I thinke of an <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> The Moderator is pleased to give: The <hi>Reformation</hi> now intended, and upon Designe; he calls it an <hi>Imperious</hi> Reformation. It is well if it be so, for if there should be a daubing in such a worke as that is so nearly concerning <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Christ,</hi> we should say of it as <hi>Ioab</hi> said in Davids works; <hi>It is abominable.</hi> We wish heartily, that Reformation may so <hi>imperiously</hi> command, that it will abate nothing of <hi>Gods</hi> Right, nor suffer any thing to stand that greives his Spirit; and is offensive to his eye. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly so it should be, and so it must be. <hi>The house that is to be bailded must be exceeding Magnificall, of same, and of glory through all Countries.</hi> [1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.22.5. Why so
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:123009:9"/>magnificall &amp; wonderfull great? <hi>For great is our God above all Gods</hi> [2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.5.] It is easily applyed, the <hi>Lord</hi> hold the hands of his Servants to the worke, their eyes to the Rule, their hearts to him; That is the way to have <hi>Peace</hi> againe, which the shedding of bloud and abominable Idolatries have taken from the Earth. The <hi>Lord</hi> fill his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants with his <hi>Spirit,</hi> make them compleat for this great businesse, It is for their <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Christ,</hi> a <hi>great God</hi> above all <hi>Gods;</hi> blessed for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have one word more to say to my owne heart and to the <hi>Moderatour:</hi> Let us cease from our owne wisedome, from seeming wiser than our Teachers, and giving Rules to our betters: nor let us be too bold with our <hi>fellow Subjects</hi> neither; they may bee directed by Reason too, and happily by a better guide; Let us looke to our selves, and into our owne hearts, pry narrowly there, what wee have done to make the breach wider, and to let in wrath upon our brethren: upon true search we shall lay hands upon our mouthes, smite upon our thighes, and be humbled even unto dust: and all our worke will be to make our Peace with our <hi>God;</hi> In his name who can repaire, and make up the Breach though wide as the Sea: when every one shall doe so in his owne particular, <hi>God</hi> will give us Peace; It shall come in as a River, and righteousnesse as the waves of the Sea. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Let him</hi> take hold of my strength <hi>that</hi> he may make Peace with Me: and he shall make Peace with Me.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Isay.</hi> 27.5.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Scias. Eum pessimè dicere qui optimè placeat malis, cum optimè dicere qui maxim, placeat bonis.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Plin. Ep.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>A Postcript.</head>
               <p>IN this Treaty of peace, we should looke upon the Kings Majesty as the principall, but being not Himselfe, but ingaged to a Partie, who pretend Loyalty yet drive their owne ends to the the ruine of their King and his Kingdoms: We looke upon them, even the Atheists in three Kingdomes, the Papists all the world over; And doe affirme from Sacred testimonie, That we can accommodate a peace with them upon no better termes, then we can make peace with the Devill.</p>
               <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>